NYSUT General Officers Records 6174/017
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT General Officers Records
1887-2006
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/017
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence.
A large part of the file concentrates on the early 1970s process of disaffiliation by NYSTA/NYSUT from the National Education Association and subsequent years of rivalry. Later records focus on reports and testimony by president Tom Hobart, vice president Antonia Cortese, executive vice president Herb Magidson, and other officers on issues such as teacher compensation, teacher certification, and health insurance.
7744992
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 30, 2013
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Scope and Contents
Materials re merger with AFT/UFT and disaffiliation with NEA, 1972-1976; early documents of teachers union, 1887-1971; some later materials, mostly about teacher competency, certification, and compensation, 1962-2000; testimony of NYSUT officers, 1978-2006
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6174/017 AV: NYSUT's General Officers. Audio-Visual Materials 6174/017 MB: NYSUT's General Officers. Memorabilia. 6174/017 P: NYSUT's General Officers Photographs All other 6174 collections
Teachers' union, New York (State); Cortese, Antonia; Hobart, Thomas Y. Jr.; Magidson, Herb; New York State United Teachers. Archives
7744992
- History Project; Disaffiliation; Unification; Staff-Line; Pamphlets (Box 1)
  - NYSUT History Project, 1988-1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    List of NYSUT officers and associates to be interviewed for oral history project, as of 11/13/90; memo from Tony Bifaro re approach to interview process, November 13, 1990; document, Use of Interview in a Variety of Forms as Script, Anecdote, and "Sound Byte," 11/2/88; memos to individuals selected for interview, March 31, 1992; sample interview data sheets (containing biographical information for NYSUT general counsel Bernard Ashe, NYS AFL-CIO Secretary-Treasurer Paul Cole, NYSUT first vice president Antonia Cortese, second vice president Walter Dunn, Jr., executive vice president Herb Magidson, NYSUT president Tom Hobart) with cover letter to Tony Bifaro from interns conducting the interviews, n.d.; questions for oral history participants; questions for the oral history interview with Tom Hobart; A Chronology of the History of NYSTA & NYSUT
  - NYSUT History Project-Leon Liberman, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    List of NYSUT History Project items in warehouse, summer 1989; notes for the plan by Crystal Toller, summer 1989, with appendices; cover memo from Tony Bifaro to Leon Lieberman, Jim Wood, and Peter Bloespflug, referencing survey of work and recommendations by intern Crystal Toller, September 13, 1989; letter from Tom Hobart to Leon Lieberman re NYSUT History Project, scheduled interview with graduate student intern, July 16, 1990; letter from Hobart to Lieberman re inappropriate interview questions that had escaped his attention, dealing with the 1978 NYSUT Convention, requesting that he disregard them, November 2, 1989; edited draft of "please disregard" letter, apparently for delivery to all interviewees; list of questions for oral history participants, re 1972 merger and 1976 disaffiliation; letter from Hobart to Lieberman, requesting participation in oral interviews for history project, November 1, 1989; cover letter from Hobart to Lieberman, requesting that he review the draft text of NYSUT history, The Evolution of NYSUT and Its Role in Educational Reform, by Gail Westover, December 20, 1989
  - NYSUT History Research Originals, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Newspaper clippings from New York Teacher re disaffiliation/merger with NEA/AFT
  - NYSUT Disaffiliation, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence between Tom Hobart and other NYSUT officers with NEA president John Royer, local leaders, re competing NEA in New York Project, October 28 and November 12, impending NYC default, October 31 and November 26; NYSUT Issues and Facts flyers; pro-Hobart-Shanker poster, Unity with the Unity Team; clipping of cover of NEA Provocator, "NYSUT Leadership Fractures Teacher Unity," December 1975; STATEMENT newsletter of Shenendehowa Teachers Association, with statements submitted by rank-and-file teachers pro and con disaffiliation, April 9, 1976
  - NYSUT Disaffiliation Binder, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Materials re disaffiliation with NEA (date of compilation not indicated); includes sections on history, structure, NYEA/NEA service, anti-NYSUT/AFT, pension, legislature, quotas, list of issues from anti-NYSUT perspective: "it shows the types of literature and materials NYEA/NEA are using" (noted in the foreword)
  - NYSUT Disaffiliation and Services Binder, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Correspondence between NYSUT president Tom Hobart and National Education Association president John Royer re disaffiliation, March- April 1976; tabbed sections re NYSUT service departments: Field Services, Legislative, Legal Services, Membership Benefits; Research and Educational Services, Membership Account
  - NYSTA Unification, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Unification Questions and Answers; map of NYSTA election districts; notification letter to locals from co-presidents Tom Hobart and Albert Shanker re membership in NYSUT, February 3, 1973
  - NYSTA-Unity Merger, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Legal summons and complaint against New York State Teachers Association and American Arbitration Association, June 7, 1972; article in New York magazine, "Is It Still OK to Hate Albert Shanker?" October 25, 1971, with cover memo to NYSTA Cabinet members, February 10, 1972; memo to NYSTA president Tom Hobart, vice presidents Rogers and Cortese, and NYSTA Board of Directors re board actions re merger with UTNY (United Teachers of New York), February 15; confidential proposals to Albert Shanker from Tom Hobart for merger of New York State Teachers Association and United Teachers of New York State, January 4; Remarks by Dr. White during Merger Discussion at the Board of Directors Meeting, February 12, with cover memo to professional staff members of the NYSTA Department of Studies (sic) and Professional Services, noting rumor mill, February 25; confidential memo to Tom Hobart from R. I. Allen and D. C. McKillip, requesting that assistant directors be kept apprised of developments in merger talks, March 3; Notice of a Meeting of Members of the New York State Teachers Association to Adopt a Plan of Consolidation, June 3, with attached Plan of Consolidation of New York State Teachers Association and United Teachers of New York State Forming New York Congress of Teachers and cover flyer re registration for Special House of Delegates, June 17; trifold brochure, National Education Association Actions on the Affiliation of Federation-Association Merged Unions, with attached letter from NEA, December 21; handwritten notes
  - Barrett Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Campaign brochure for Catherine Barrett for NEA Vice President/President-Elect; Barrett resume; letter from NYSUT president Tom Hobart to Barrett, demanding explanation for Barrett's support for the re-election of Republican governor Wilson, with attached newspaper clippings quoting anti-union statements, November 8, 1974; letter to Hobart from Barrett, thanking him and NYSUT for crystal bowl, July 16, 1973
  - Barrett Correspondence Union Release Objection Letter, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Letters between NEA president Catherine Barrett and NYSUT president Tom Hobart re criticism of NYSUT and UFT president Albert Shanker in NEA publication Union Release #154 (November 13, 1972)
  - Cortese-Candidate for NEA VP/President Election, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Letter from Cortese, announcing that she would not be a candidate again, outlining concerns about needed NEA reforms, June 17, 1974; nominating speech for Toni Cortese, by Tom Hobart, July 3, 1973, and earlier draft with handwritten edits; NYSUT press release, "Toni Cortese Running for President-Elect of NEA," April 2, 1973; letter to NEA delegates from Tom Hobart and Albert Shanker, endorsing Toni Cortese and Walter Tice for Executive Committee of the NEA, noting endorsement by NYSUT Board of Directors, June 20 1973; biographical and platform statements for Cortese and Tice; related correspondence
  - Letter to Local Presidents from Hobart and NYSUT, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    November 26, 1975. Letter outlining NYSUT position in disaffiliation, history of NYSTA/NEA and UTNY/AFT rivalry, external attacks on teachers, signed by Tom Hobart, president, Al Shanker, executive vice president, Toni Cortese, second vice president, and rest of board
  - Letter to Local Presidents from John Royer, NEA President, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    November 26, 1975. Letter denouncing NYSUT disaffiliation, urging local presidents to retain affiliation with NEA
  - Letter to Roger and Local Presidents from Hobart, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    December 11, 1975. Letter proposing retraction of plans to establish competing organization (NEA in New York Project) and other preconditions to reconciliation; cover letter to local presidents
  - Hobart/Royer Correspondence NEA in NY Project, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    October-November 1975. Letter from NEA president John Royer to NYSUT president Tom Hobart, describing NEA in NY Project, October 28; letter from Hobart to Royer, discussing initial reaction to project, October 31; letter from Hobart to Royer, notifying him of vote by NYSUT Board of Directors to reject the NEA in NY Project, November 12, 1975; letter from Royer to Hobart calling decision an overreaction, proposing to meet with board, November 18; telegram to Royer from Hobart, informing him that he could speak at board meeting that evening, November 19
  - Letter from Hobart to Board Members against Disaffiliation, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    December 9, 1975. Letter to six board members who voted against disaffiliation, requesting article for New York Teacher representing their point of view
  - Letter from Tom Pisa, Buffalo Teachers Federation, on Disaffiliation, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    December 23, 1975. Letter to colleagues deploring the disaffiliation action of NYSUT Board of Directors
  - Hopkins Letter of Resignation, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Letter to NYSUT president Tom Hobart from Ned Hopkins, resigning position at NYSUT, enumerating problems re Albert Shanker's influence on the organization, May 8, 1978
  - Board Notes on President's Report on NEA, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    November 22, 1975. Handwritten outline
  - New York Educators Association/NEA, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Copies of NYEA Advocate and NYEA Leader; letter to colleagues from Reginald M. Washington, past president of Bellport Teachers Association, calling NYSUT publication "What Price Quotas?" racist, criticizing NYSUT's failure to adopt NEA affirmative action ("minority guarantee") programs, denouncing NYSUT leadership as indifferent to black teachers, alleging several related offenses, n.d.; letter to William Smith, director of Teacher Corps, U.S. Office of Education, from Chuck Santelli, director of NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services, describing NYSUT/NYEA dispute, May 26, 1976; list of NYEA officers and regional directors and votes on whether to disaffiliate with NYSUT, and list of NYSUT Board of Directors members and their votes on disaffiliation from NEA, with cover memo from Tom Hobart, May 26, 1976; correspondence from Mort Bahr, vice president, Communication Workers of America, to New York Educators Association and Newsday, noting support for NYSUT and not NEA/NYEA, June-July; memo re Bahr from John DeGregorio, Suffolk coordinator, to Tom Hobart, July 19; "open letter" mailer to teachers from NEA president John Royer denouncing NYSUT decision to disaffiliate; NYEA member presidential preference ballot (Carter vs. Ford), with flyer urging participation in presidential endorsement process; list of NEA officers in New York State; NEA ad in Newsday, "The Bored of Education," claiming students were no longer engaged in learning, NEA was there to help, February 12, 1976; document, "About NEA's New Affiliate in New York" (NYEA, competing with NYSUT), with attached map and list of NYSUT staff remaining with NEA as of March 8, 1976; untitled pro-NEA document directed at teachers, with map of NEA service centers around New York State; Daily News clipping, "Teacher vs. Teacher: The unions declare uncivil war," March 11, 1976; confidential memo from Tom Hobart to NYSUT officers reporting on first meeting of NYEA board, March 6, 1976; agenda for organizational meeting of NYEA, April 1, 1976; document, "NYEA Answers to your Questions on Continuing NEA Affiliation," with frequently asked questions re disaffiliation, minority guarantee, New York Project, et al.; NYEA document, "A Bill of Rights for Teachers & an Interim Governance Document: A Proposal for Consideration by the Teachers of New York," March 1976
  - NEA Project on Educational Neglect, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Bound volume, Project 1975: Educational Neglect: On-Site Research Reports, Working Papers for Participants, Conference on Educational Neglect, February 15-18, 1975; associated brochures; letters from NEA president James A. Harris to NYSUT president Tom Hobart, inviting NYSUT to send a delegation to the national conference, October 18, 1974, and acknowledging NYSUT's reluctance to participate, January 27, 1975; reply from Hobart that the conference would expose problems but did not offer realistic programs to solve them, December 20, 1974
  - NYSTA Staff-Line, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Original weekly newsletters for NYSTA staff; memo to all NYSTA staff re establishment of weekly staff newsletter, September 28, 1970; memo to NYSUT Board of Directors re personnel reductions, July 25, 1977
  - NYSTA/ NYSUT Staffline, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Issues of Staffline, NYSTA employee newsletters, nos. 63-93 (November 16, 1971 - May 10, 1972), and Vol. 1, No. 1 of NYSUT Staffline, March 20, 1973; nos. 2 and 3; Headquarters Edition, including invitation to toast new name of organization from NTSTA to NYSUT, April 30, 1973
  - NEA Defense Commission Pamphlets, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Brochures of the NEA National Commission for the Defense of Democracy through Education, describing purpose and activities: to investigate controversies, critics of public education, and "alleged subversive teaching and to expose any teacher whose attitude is found to be inimical to the best interests of our country"; "Admiral Rickover on American Education: An Analysis of His Viewpoints," by Richard I. Miller, reprinted from the Journal of Teacher Education, vol. X, no. 3, September 1959
  - NEA Pamphlets, 1953-1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Constitution of the New York State Teachers Association, in effect as of December 1, 1948, as amended November 22, 1949; Constitution of the New York State Teachers Association to be the Articles of Incorporation, November 1953; Constitution and Bylaws of the New York State Teachers Association, effective September 1, 1954, amended November 1954, November 1955, November 1966; Report of the Task Force on Human Rights, 1968; The Affirmative Action Plan for the NEA, 1975; Summary of Centennial, n.d., c. 1957
  - NYSUT and UFT Pamphlets, 1967-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    NYSUT Educational Issues series 1, Class Size; 2, Teacher Evaluation; 3, Teacher Aids, n.d., c. 1973; UFT publication, Towards Dignity: A Brief History of the United Federation of Teachers, by Thomas R. Brooks, 1967; NYSUT benefits brochures: Disability Income Protection Plan (Mutual of Omaha); Hilton 1976 Student-Faculty Plan; Horace Mann Homeowner's Insurance for NYSUT Members
  - NYSTA Correspondence-Invitations to Speak at Various Meetings, 1955-1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Letter to NYSTA executive secretary G. Howard Goold from U.S. Senator Irving M. Ives, pledging support for federal aid for school construction, January 24, 1955, with attached text of Senate bill; invitation to public hearing of the NYS Joint Legislative Committee on Problems of the Aging, from committee chair Thomas Desmond, November 30, 1953; letter from U.S. Senator John F. Kennedy to NYSTA Professional Services director Zoraida Weeks, regretting being unable to speak at annual meeting of the Southern Zone of NYSTA on October 17, noting re-election campaign required him to be in Massachusetts, January 28, 1958; letter to Goold from Eleanor Roosevelt, regretting being unable to attend luncheon, November 14, 1958; letter from Cardinal Spellman, Archbishop of New York, noting that Msgr. John J. Voight, Secretary for Education in the Archdiocese of New York, would represent him at luncheon, November 18, 1958; regrets from U.S. Representative to the United Nations Henry Cabot Lodge, January 27, 1960, and March 17, 1961; U.N. Under-Secretary Ralph Bunche, May 21, 1959; U.S. Senator Margaret Chase-Smith, March 4, 1959; Adlai Stevenson, March 10, 1959; Jackie Robinson, March 13, 1968; tentative acceptance from Saturday Review editor Norman Cousins, noting speaker's fee, February 6, 1958; tentative acceptance from Supreme Court Justice William J. Brennan, Jr., September 22, 1966; various officials from the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, state commissioners of education, editors and publishers, college presidents and other academics
  - NYSTA-Proceedings, 1887-1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Program for Annual Banquet of the House of Delegates of NYSTA, 1954; Proceedings of the forty-second annual meeting of the New York State Teachers' Association, July 6, 7, and 8, 1987; forty-fourth annual meeting, July 2 and 3, 1889; forty-fifth annual meeting, July 7, 8, and 9, 1890; forty-sixth annual meeting, July 6, 7, and 8, 1891
  - NYSTA/NEA Code of Ethics, 1931-1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Pamphlets including "Implementing the Code of Ethics of the Education Profession and Strengthening Professional Rights," NEA, June 1964, and "Enforcement of the Code of Ethics of the Education Profession," NEA, 1969; Code of Ethics for the Teachers of the State of New York, November 1931; The Dr. Frank Pierpont Graves Oath for Teachers, January 1952; recommendation to the NYSTA Board of Directors by the Ethical Practices Committee to amend the Joint Code of Ethics stipulating that the school board adopts policy which conforms to statutory limitations, judicial interpretations, rules of the Regents and regulations of the Commissioner of Education, and the teacher cooperates in the observance of policy, May 11- 12, 1962; copy of Joint Code of Ethics of the New York State School Boards Association and the New York State Teachers Association (c. 1950 and c. 1964 versions); NYSTA Codes of Ethics: Their Interpretation and A Bill of Rights for Teachers, third revised edition, 1961 (eighth printing December 1968); paper, "State Responsibility in the Ethics and Practice of Teaching," by N. E. Kullman, Jr., n.d., c. 1962; National Education Association of the United States Committee on Professional Ethics "Professional Ethics Quiz," December 1959; newsletter, NYSTA Know-How for Local Teachers Association, featuring article, "Ethics Dignify a Profession," n.d., c. early 1960s
  - NYSTA Management Surveys, 1952-1971 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Staff Organization and Operations Report and Recommendations to the Board of Directors of the New York State Teachers Association, submitted by Francis J. White, Jr., Executive Secretary, February 5, 1971, with cover note from minutes re action taken on the plan, and cover memo to staff from Nathan Kullman re staff reorganization, February 9, 1971; Management Survey of the New York State Teachers' Association, August 1969, with cover notes and memo to staff from Nathan Kullman re staff interviews for survey, July 9, 1969, and Article XIII of agreement between NYSTA and staff organization re management study and re-evaluation of positions and salaries; memo from executive secretary G. Howard Goold to NYSTA Board of Directors re Highlights of Membership Survey Findings, noting undefined image of NYSTA among members, October 24, 1968; Summary Report of Membership Mail Questionnaire and Interview Study, by Dr. George A. Sanborn & Associates, Inc., n.d.; Additional Analysis of Data from Membership Mail Questionnaire and Interview Study, October 1968; excerpts from Board of Directors meeting minutes (?) re decision to hire consulting firm, 1967-68; memo from Goold to Board of Directors recommending management study of NYSTA, February 1968; report and cover letter of transmittal to Goold re study of NYSTA headquarters operations, August 4, 1952
  - NYSTA Board of Directors, 1957-1967 (Box 1, Folder 31)